### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/jamesgosling (LinkedIn)

nighthacks.com/roller/jag (Blog) www.google.com/search (Other)

### Top Skills

Mac

Internet of Things (IoT)

Graphics

### Honors-Awards

John Von Neumann Medal

**Fellow** 

Officer of the Order of Canada

Member

Software Systems Award

### **Publications**

The Algebraic Manipulation of Constraints

Oak (Java) Language Specification v0.2

### **Patents**

"Method and apparatus for automatically archiving and clearing intellectual property"

# James Gosling

Software Engineer

Redwood City, California, United States

# Summary

I've worked on all kinds of software, from ground analysis for telemetry from the ISIS II satellite to the original Unix Emacs, the NeWS window system, and the Java Programming language. My PhD thesis was on "The Algebraic Manipulation of Constraints". I had some wonderful years at Sun Microsystems, where I was best known as the original developer of the Java programming language. I spent over 5 years hacking the control software of autonomous ocean-going robots. I've just finished 7 years at Amazon Web Services and I'm now retired.

Specialties: Graphics, Languages, Embedded Systems, Distributed Systems, ...

# Experience

Amazon Web Services
Distinguished Engineer
May 2017 - July 2024 (7 years 3 months)
Palo Alto, CA

I mostly worked on IoT projects. A product that I initiated and launched is AWS Greengrass, https://aws.amazon.com/greengrass/

Liquid Robotics
Chief Software Architect
August 2011 - May 2017 (5 years 10 months)
Sunnyvale, California

Hacking ocean-going robots and housing their data in a cloud.

DIRTT Environmental Solutions Director 2003 - May 2017 (14 years)

Member of the board of directors.

Google

Software Engineer

March 2011 - August 2011 (6 months)

Free-floating curmudgeon

Sun Microsystems

26 years

Fellow & CTO of Client Software Group

1984 - April 2010 (26 years)

Oversaw the developing engineering of later versions of Java; lots of public appearances and presentations to customers.

Engineer

1984 - 2010 (26 years)

NeWS window System; assorted graphics rendering routines; then Java...

Sun Labs

VP and Fellow

January 1999 - January 2002 (3 years 1 month)

Research on semantically driven software development tools. Produced the Real

Time Specification for Java. Built the Sun Labs document archive and legal clearance system.

JavaSoft

Chief Scientist and Fellow

January 1995 - January 1999 (4 years 1 month)

Technical and business guidance of the Java efforts at Sun. Duties were fairly evenly split between business strategy, technical review and public presentations

& amp; evangelization.

1994! Lead Architect, LiveOak project, Sun Labs.

Leading the engineering team in the application of FirstPerson technology to the

internet. This was launched as the HotJava browser and Java programming language.

FirstPerson Inc

Chief Scientist

January 1992 - January 1994 (2 years 1 month)

Lead design team to produce software for the consumer electronics market, particularly focused on the set-top and interactive television solutions. Effort included developing a runtime for set-tops and content development and preparation tools.

### FirstPerson

Engineer

1992 - 1994 (2 years)

Did general software engineering, including the design and implementation of the Oak programming language, which was eventually renamed to Java.

### Green project, Sun Labs

Lead Architect

January 1991 - January 1992 (1 year 1 month)

Investigated software requirements, designed, implemented and demonstrated prototype of a consumer electronics software platform. Oversaw all software development including the guidance of a 12 person team. Personally implemented

a compiler for a safe, multi-threaded, distributed, object-oriented programming language (related to C++) named Oak. Very positive customer response lead to

the formation

### Window Systems

Lead Architect

January 1984 - January 1989 (5 years 1 month)

Designed and implemented the Networked Extensible Window System (NeWS), a

distributed window system based on PostScript. The PostScript language was used as the basis for interprocess communication, allowing computation to migrate from the client to the server. This included writing a complete PostScript

clone and guiding the Folio hinted font scaling technology. The combination of the

PostScript clone and the font scaling technology enabled Sun to create software

to drive inexpensive printers using the CPU power of the desktop, thus instigating

suns printing business.

#### **IBM**

Engineer

January 1983 - August 1984 (1 year 8 months)

Worked on loan to the CMU/ITC project & consulted on the PC/RT product from IBM. If only that had listened to me!!

J.Watson Research Center

Member of Technical Staff T

January 1983 - January 1984 (1 year 1 month)

Designed and implemented the Andrew window system (the first distributed window system) and the Andrew user-interface toolkit (the first document based

object oriented toolkit)

Carnegie Mellon University - ITC

Engineer

1983 - 1984 (1 year)

Designed and implemented the first version of the Andrew window system and user interface toolkit.

### **CMU**

**Graduate Student** 

1977 - 1983 (6 years)

PhD in computer science; Ported BSD unix to a 16 CPU symmetric multiprocessor built from PDP11/40Es; implemented Unix Emacs; which eventually became GNU emacs; implemented a Pascal compiler on Multics (a contract job); Designed and implemented a compiler for a language called MUMBLE for a wide-instruction horizontal bit-slice microprocessor (truly a bizarre, but fast, machine)

Herminet Inc

Software Engineer

1981 - 1982 (1 year)

Designed and implemented an intelligent mail handling system.

This eventually became the MHS system from Action Technologies.

# Education

Carnegie Mellon University

PhD, Computer Science · (1977 - 1983)

Carnegie Mellon University

MS, Computer Science · (1977 - 1983)

University of Calgary

BSc (Honors), Computer Science · (1973 - 1977)